Okay, so one way to represent this trade-off between something that's common
국소적으로 흔함과 전역적 희귀를
locally but rare globally is something that's called TF-IDF or
나타내는 방법 중 하나는 TF-IDF라 불리는 것인데
Term frequency- inverse document frequency.
단어 빈도-역문서 빈도입니다
Okay, so first let's describe what term frequency is, and here what we're gonna do
단어 빈도를 먼저 설명하자면
is look locally, we're looking just at the document that the person is currently
국소적으로 봐서 지금 읽고 있는 문서에서
reading and we simply count the number of words like we did.
단순하게 단어수를 셉니다
So this is just our word count factor.
단어수 벡터가 되죠
But then what we're gonna do is, we're gonna
그다음엔
downweight this factor base on something called the Inverse Document Frequency.
역문서 빈도로 벡터 가중치를 낮춥니다
So for this, we're gonna look at all documents in our corpus and
말뭉치의 모든 문서에서
were gonna compute the following thing, which is log of
말뭉치의 문서수 나누기 1 더하기
the number of documents in the corpus divided by 1
대상 단어 포함 문서수에
plus the number of documents that contain the word that we're looking at.
로그를 씌워 계산합니다
Okay, so let's think a little bit about why we have this form.
왜 이런 형태가 되는지 생각해 보죠
So first, let's think about a very common word.
흔한 상용어를 들어 봅시다
So, a word appearing in many documents.
많은 문서에 등장하는 단어죠
Well what happens?
어떻게 되나요?
We end up with the log of some large #
큰 숫자 / 1 + 다른 큰 숫자 전체에
/ 1 + another large number, and
로그를 씌우면
we'll say this is approximately log of 1,
대략적으로 log1에 근접하게 되는데
which is equal to 0.
0이죠
So what we see here, is that we're gonna be very, very strongly downweighting all
그러니까 엄청난 빈도수의 단어는
the way to zero, the counts of any word that appears extremely frequently.
거의 0에 가깝게 가중치가 줄어드는 겁니다
Where that appears in all of our documents.
모든 문서에 등장하는 단어요
Okay, but in contrast, if we have a rare word,
반대로 희소 단어가 있고
were gonna have log of, I would say, a large number,
문서수가 많다고 가정하면
assuming we have a large number of documents that
큰 숫자를
we were searching over divided by 1 + a small number,
1 + 작은 숫자로 나눈 값의 로그죠
and this is gonna be, or to say some largish number,
이건 대충 큰 숫자가 될 겁니다
or a not a zero or a small number.
0이나 작은 숫자는 아니겠죠
And the reason that we have this one here, is the fact that we can't assume that
여기 1이 있는 이유는 문서의 모든 단어가
every word appears in any document in the corpus.
말뭉치에 있다고 가정할 수 없기 때문입니다
So there might be some word in the vocabulary that doesn't appear
말뭉치 어디에도 등장하지 않는 단어가
anywhere in our corpus.
문서에 있을 수 있죠
And so we wanna avoid dividing by 0.
그러므로 0으로 나누는 일만은 피해야 합니다
Okay, so let's look at an example where there's the index for
the란 단어의 인덱스가 있는 예제를 들 텐데
the word the, and let's say that the appears.
the라는 단어가 대충
I don't know. Something like a thousand times in
대상 문서에서 1000번 등장하고
the document that I'm looking at, and then there's the word messi.
그중 메시란 단어도 있다고 합시다
Messi appears five times.
메시는 5번 등장합니다
Okay, now I'm gonna look at computing the inverse document frequency for that word.
이제 이 단어의 역문서 빈도를 계산합니다
So the word the,
단어 the가
let's assume that the word the appears in every document in the corpus.
말뭉치의 모든 문서에서 등장한다고 가정합니다
Well, really every document except one, so I can do some easy math here.
하나만 뺀 모든 문서라고 해서 계산을 쉽게 하죠
So, when I'm looking at this entry,
이 항목을 보면
I'm gonna compute log of the number of documents in the corpus and
말뭉치 문서수의 로그를 계산할건데
let's assume that we have 64 documents in this corpus.
말뭉치에 문서가 64개 있다고 가정하죠
And then we have 1+, and I assume that the word the didn't appear in
그리고 1을 더해준 다음 단어 the가
one of these 64 documents, must have been a pretty short document.
전체 문서 64개 중 한 문서에서 등장하지 않았다고 가정합니다 꽤 짧은 문서였겠죠
And so, what this gives us is the 0 that we talking about before.
그러면 아까 설명드린 바와 같이 결과가 0이 됩니다
So the the gets downweighted completely by zero.
가중치가 완전히 0으로 내려오는거죠
In contrast, when we look at Messi, let's assume that
반대로 메시를 예로 들어보면
again we have some 64 total documents and
다시 총 64개의 문서에서 단어 메시가
lets assume that the word Messi appears only in three of these documents,
이 중 문서 3개에 등장한다고 가정하면
so we get log of 16,
로그 16이 되는데
which if we use log base two gives us four.
로그2면 답이 4가 됩니다
Okay, so this is our term frequency, and
이게 두 단어의 단어 빈도와
our inverse document frequency for these two words.
역문서 빈도가 됩니다
And when we code to compute the term frequency, inverse document frequency, for
특정 문서에 대한 새로운 표현법이 될
the specific document which is gonna be our new representation of this document,
단어 빈도와 역문서 빈도를 계산하려면
we simply multiply these two factors together.
두 벡터를 곱합니다
So theres some numbers here, where the word the,
여기 단어 the가 0이 되고
turns into a 0 and then these are some other numbers and then the word
여기선 단어 메시의
Messi is gonna be upweighted, so a weight of 20.
가중치가 올라가서 20이 됩니다
And again,
다시 한번
there's some other computation we're doing for all the other words in our vocabulary.
어휘의 다른 모든 단어에 해야 하는 계산이 있습니다
But the point that we wanna make here is the fact that these very common words like
중요한 점은 흔한 상용어인 the의 가중치는 내려가고
the, get downweighted and the rare and
희귀하면서 잠재적으로 매우 중요한 단어인
potentially very important words like Messi are getting upweighted.
메시의 가중치는 올라간다는 점입니다